Boker tov, so today's daf is daf yud, we pick up on
the close to the bottom of amud bet, so we have a
few pages to catch up, a few lines to catch up,
and we are on,
I guess we'll have to start again from ביי רב אבין. Bei
Rav Avin. So it's 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, about 13 lines
from the
bottom, the line starts with the word חמישית. chamishit. So it's ביי
רב אבין, Bei Rav Avin, middle of that line, right under the
פסוק pasuk אם המקדיש דש. Im hamakdish dash.
So we had just said that the הלכה halacha is that you,
when you redeem something, you add a fifth, the Torah says, and
we had said in the name of רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi that that's only if you are redeeming the thing
you sanctified. But if you are redeeming something to which you transferred
the sanctity to, but you'd already redeemed one object with another object,
I gave the example yesterday, so I sanctified my Ford, then I
redeemed it, so I redeemed it on something that was a fifth
more, so I redeemed it on my Camry. So now the question
is I'm going to redeem my Camry, do I add a fifth
to that? So the answer is no because I didn't directly sanctify
my Camry, I only transferred the קדושה. kedusha. And now we're going
to ask a question which sort of plays on this whole strange
case that we dealt with yesterday about an אשם asham and changing
its קדושה kedusha and so on. So let's take a look. ביי
רב אבין, Bei Rav Avin, so רב אבין Rav Avin asked: הפריש
אשם להתכפר בו. hifrish asham le-hitkaper bo. So you separated, designated out,
you sanctified an אשם asham to atone, והוא מום, ve-hu mum, and
he added a fifth. Now here we're not dealing with תמורה, temurah,
here again the issue is about adding a fifth, so you redeemed
it, which you're allowed to do, and you redeemed it and you
transferred it to an animal that is worth a fifth more.
Let's figure out why you had to put in an extra fifth.
No, you do put in,
yes, it is correct that normally the case that we assume that
the time when the Torah says you add a fifth is when
it's קדשי בדק הבית, kadshei bedek habayit, not קדשי מזבח. kadshei mizbe'ach.
Nevertheless, it's implicit from this גמרא Gemara that even when you're redeeming
a sacrifice with a blemish you add a fifth. The גמרא Gemara
learns it out in another place, the fact that in that context
the Torah says: ואם מבהמה אשר לא יקריבו ממנה קרבן לה', ve-im
mibehema asher lo yakrivu mimena korban l'Hashem, that if it's an animal
that you won't bring a קרבן korban then you also redeem it
and add a fifth. Now you could have assumed that meant that
you sanctified such an animal to the בדק הבית, bedek habayit, to
the treasury. But the חז"ל Chazal understand no, it means you sanctified
an animal and you can't bring it as a קרבן korban because
it got a blemish and that you add a fifth. So the
assumption is absolutely correct, although it is a little unexpected, that you
add a fifth even when you are redeeming a קרבן. korban. Okay,
so you sanctified this animal, this אשם, asham, you redeemed it, you
added a fifth, okay, you did it in a way that wasn't
תמורה temurah but that was actually פדיון pidyon that was allowed, וחיללו
על חבירו, ve-chilalo al chavero,
and you transferred it to another animal. ונתכפר באשם אחר, ve-nitkaper be-asham
acher,
and then, so now this other animal is now not the original
animal, and now something else happens, that it got lost, you used
another אשם, asham, וניתק זה לעולה, ve-nitak zeh l'olah, and then this
thing therefore transferred its identity from an אשם asham to an עולה,
olah, just like the complex case we dealt with yesterday. So what's
the question? מהו שיוסיף עליו חומש? Mah hu she-yosif alav chomesh? If
now this animal gets a blemish and I want to redeem it,
do I add a fifth? On the one hand, I don't add
a fifth unless it's the animal I directly sanctified, not some derivative
קדושה, kedusha, and this is derivative because it comes from the original
animal which I already did a fifth, added a fifth to and
I redeemed once. On the other hand, this is a little bit
different because it transformed from an אשם asham to an עולה, olah,
so maybe I will not look at it as derivative, maybe I'll
look at it as something new. Okay, and what's the הלכה? halacha?
So let's take a look. אמר אביי: Amar Abaye: מאי קמיבעיא ליה?
mai ka mibaya lei? What's the question? אי שתי גופי מקדושה אחת
קמיבעיא ליה, Ishtei gufi mi-kedusha achas ka mibaya lei, meaning there's a
hybrid case, why don't you ask about each of its component parts?
What are each of its component parts? אי שתי גופי מקדושה אחת
קמיבעיא ליה, Ishtei gufi mi-kedusha achas ka mibaya lei, if you want
to know about two different bodies but one קדושה, kedusha, meaning a
simple case of transferring the קדושה kedusha and now it's in a
second animal, תיבעי בלא נתכפר, tibaya belo nitkaper, ask the question without
the case of having changed from an אשם asham to an עולה.
olah. Why did you have to add that to make it more
complex? אי שתי קדושות וגוף אחד, Ishtei kedushas ve-guf echad, if your
question is about transforming from an אשם asham to an עולה olah
and even in one body קמיבעיא ליה, ka mibaya lei, תיבעי בלא
מום, tibaya belo mum, ask it without a blemish. Why did you
have to give a complex case? So the גמרא Gemara says the
same thing it said yesterday, רב אבין Rav Avin and רב אבין
Rav Avin would say חדא מגו חדא קמיבעיא ליה. chada mi-go chada
ka mibaya lei. He's asking one built on the other, meaning yes,
he knows if he asked one thing the answer might be obvious
and therefore he's adding what if it has two things different with
it, then the answer is less obvious. אם תמצא לומר, Im timtza
lomar, אי שתי גופי וקדושה אחת, ishtei gufi ve-kedusha achas, לא, lo,
if you'll say that when it has two separate bodies but one
קדושה, kedusha, meaning the first one was redeemed and got transferred, that
that case you don't add a fifth, why? משום דההיא קדושה איתוסף
בחדא זימנא, mishum de-hahi kedusha itosef be-chada zimna, because you've already added
a fifth the first time when it was in the first animal
and this is the same קדושה kedusha being transferred, so now you're
not going to add a fifth the second time, that was our
whole point.
חומש. chomesh. He tells us משום דבהאי קדושה איתוסף חדא זימנא חומש
Mishum de-be-hei kedusha itosef chada zimna chomesh that you've already added a
חומש, chomesh, שני גופי שתי קדושות מאי? Shene gufe shte kedushos mai?
But what if not only is it in a different animal, but
it's a different type of a קדושה kedusha transformed from an אשם
asham to an עולה, ola, may that is something new and תיקו
teiku the גמרא Gemara says okay we don't know the answer. Now
I want to point out something, it is a very bizarre because
I was waiting for Michael to stop me on this, because how
could it say we had two, we wanted to ask each, you
know, one component and then made it more complex. What would have
been the question in the first case? The first animal got a
blemish, you transferred it to the second,
why is that a question? That's exactly the הלכה halacha where we
say you only add a fifth to the first, to the first
case, not in the second thing it's been transferred to. So why
did it say well, first of all you add a fifth to
the thing it's been transferred to, and even if you say no,
what if it got transformed and became an עולה. ola. But the
thing is that was the exact הלכה halacha that you don't add
a fifth to the thing it's been transferred to. So רש"י Rashi
says it's a little different here. Normally when I transfer it's essentially
an equal exchange. I move the קדושה kedusha from my four and
I redeem it with my camel. Or even if it had a
blemish, I remove it from one animal with a blemish and I
transfer it to another animal. When it's essentially an equivalent exchange, then
I say I don't add a fifth on the second, from the
second thing. But here, the first animal had a blemish and wasn't
a קרבן. korban. And then I transferred it, could be brought as
a קרבן. korban. I transferred it to the second animal which was
unblemished. This animal could be brought as a קרבן. korban. So already
here the, the impact of the קדושה kedusha is slightly different because
this animal is now fit for being brought as a קרבן. korban.
So maybe that makes it enough as something new, that's why רש"י
Rashi reframes the question because now it can be brought as a
קרבן, korban, that now I, now it's enough new that I would
add a fifth. And even if you say not, what if the
קדושה kedusha went further and even transferred to be the קדושה kedusha
from an אשם asham to an עולה. ola. Okay, so that's the,
similar to the questions yesterday. Here you only add a fifth to
the first time, not the second time, when it transfers to a
different animal and a different קדושה kedusha from אשם asham to עולה,
ola, maybe it's like the first time and maybe you would add
a fifth.
How did it become from אשם asham to עולה? ola?
Because if you have an אשם asham that you misplaced and then
you brought another אשם asham instead, and then you found the one
that you had lost, then the, then an אשם asham where the
owners had, had gotten their atonement through another אשם, asham, the first
אשם asham becomes an עולה. ola. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this, לישנא אחרינא, Lishna achrina, so as we've now gotten
familiar with, in תמורה Temura you get to do a lot of
חזרה chazara when it has לישנא אחרינא, lishna achrina, which רש"י Rashi
is now being consistent and calling just if you're, if you're interested
from the time we saw this on ו' עמוד ב' vav amud
bet saying this is לשון ירושלמי, lashon Yerushalmi, and we discussed the
other day whether it literally means from the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, we don't
have a ירושלמי Yerushalmi on קדשים. Kodashim. Anyway, but it is more
of an ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael Aramaic. לישנא אחרינא, Lishna achrina, here's
another version of what we just said.
בעי רב פפא, Ba'ei Rav Papa, הפריש אשם להתכפר בו והומם, Hifrish
asham le-hiskaper bo ve-humam, you set aside an אשם asham and it
got a blemish, וחיללו על אחר, ve-chilalo al acher, and you put,
transferred it to another animal, והוסיף בו חומש, ve-hosif bo chomesh, and
of course you add a fifth like you're supposed
to, ונתכפר באשם אחר, ve-niskaper be-asham acher, and then you read and
used another קרבן, korban, another אשם, asham, coming back to David's question,
because you got atonement through another אשם, asham, וניתק זה לעולה, ve-nitak
ze le-ola, the first one now became designated for an עולה. ola.
מהו שיוסיף עליו חומש? Mahu she-yosif alav chomesh? And now this second
one got a blemish, do you add a fifth? On the one
hand, it's a different animal and a different קדושה, kedusha, so maybe
it's like a new thing, it's like the first time and you
add a fifth. But on the other hand, it's all derivative from
the first. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, הדין קמיבעיא ליה, Hadein kamiba'aya lei,
which is he asking? אי קדושה אחרת באותו גוף קמיבעיא ליה, Ei
kedusha acheres be-oso guf kamiba'aya lei, if he's asking when the קדושה
kedusha transformed in the same body, is that like a new thing?
מיבעיא ליה הומם, Miba'aya lei humam, לא
מיבעיא ליה הומם, lo miba'aya lei humam, why did you have to
give the case of a blemish? אי גוף אחד באותה קדושה קמיבעיא
ליה, Ei guf echad be-osah kedusha kamiba'aya lei, and if he's asking
the case of, again, it's the funny phrase from yesterday, one body,
but it means a different body. It's funny, again, it's a different
body with the same קדושה. kedusha. So why do you ask, then
why do you have to ask about a transforming? So the גמרא
Gemara says he's asking really two things. Okay, וכולי, ve-chulei, doesn't even
bother to write it out. So, וחיללו על אחר מהו שיוסיף עליו
חומש, ve-chilalo al acher mahu she-yosif alav chomesh, okay, let's say both
things happens, what's the story? מי אמרינן, Mi amrinan, so it's really
asking both stages. First we'll ask one. דאשם קמא הוא, De-asham kama
hu,
now there's a big question here is the גרסא, girsa, you could
say where do you add in the word לא, lo, where do
you order the אין. ein. I'm going to read it like the
שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet because it's just, it makes it the same
as the previous, which is what the לישנא אחרינא lishna achrina are
always, are always doing, they're the same as the previous. So would
you just say when you transferred it, מי אמרינן באשם קמא הוא
דלא, Mi amrinan be-asham kama hu de-lo, one minute, הוא דקמוסיף חומש,
hu de-ka-mosif chomesh, אבל בגוף אחד אף על גב דקאי באותה קדושה
אין מוסיף חומש, aval be-guf echad af al gav de-kai be-osah kedusha
ein mosif chomesh,
one minute, no, מוסיף חומש. mosif chomesh. גיוואלד, Gevald, hold on, now
I, now I lost track which way the שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet
is doing. Hold on a second. It's a real hazard.
Yeah, well I'm sure there are two different versions that are running
parallel down here. Yeah, exactly. Okay, so it's מוסיף, mosif, right. Do
you say באשם קמא הוא ד... be-asham kama hu de... just one
minute,
הוא דאינו מוסיף חומש. hu de-eino mosif chomesh. Oh, meaning okay. If
it was, yeah, okay. Anyway, if it was in the first one
you wouldn't add a fifth. But it's bizarre because the first one
you always add a fifth. You always add a fifth in the
original. That's why the that's why there's a problem here because the
the simple case of transferring it is the classic case when you
don't add a fifth. רש"י Rashi had to somehow explain why this
was a little bit different of a transfer and maybe you still.
So really what the text sort of needs to say
is באשם כמהו מוסיף חומש ובגוף אחד נמי מוסיף חומש be'asham kamohu
mosif chomesh u'veguf echad nami mosif chomesh because it's the same קדושה.
kedusha. But okay, presumably the way you have to read it is
if it was the first אשם asham and it had transformed then
you wouldn't add a fifth because then it would really be something
new. אבל בגוף אחד אף על גב דקאי באותה קדושה מוסיף חומש
aval beguf echad af al gav dekai be'ota kedusha mosif chomesh but
in a different body then you would add a fifth because at
least it's a different body. Again the funny thing is but it's
the same קדושה. kedusha. So you have to read it like רש"י
Rashi but it's somewhat a different קדושה kedusha because it's now fit
to be brought as a קרבן. korban. או דילמא o dilma or
do you say כל באותה קדושה אינו מוסיף חומש. kol be'ota kedusha
eino mosif chomesh. Now it gets easier. As long as it's the
same קדושה kedusha even in a separate animal you don't add a
fifth. Top of י"ד yud daled עמוד א'. amud aleph. Which is
the whole point, you don't add a fifth in a second animal.
ואי תמצא לומר דאפילו בגוף אחד כיון דבאותה קדושה קאי אינו מוסיף
חומש ve'im timtza lomar de'afilu beguf echad keivan de'be'ota kedusha kai eino
mosif chomesh but so even then if you say that okay even
when it's in a different body because it's the same קדושה kedusha
you don't add a fifth. אלא נתכפר באחר וניתק לעולה מהו? ela
nitkaper be'acher venittak le'olah mahu? Fine, but then what happens if not
a different body but it transformed from אשם asham to
עולה? olah? כי אינו מוסיף חומש ki eino mosif chomesh again you
see we're constantly fixing the text. כי אינו מוסיף חומש באותו גוף
ובאותה קדושה. ki eino mosif chomesh be'oto guf u've'ota kedusha. When do
you not add a fifth? When it's just a derivative of the
original קדושה. kedusha. אבל בקדושה אחרת לא aval bikdusha acheret lo but
when it's a different קדושה kedusha the story would be different.
או דילמא כיון דבאותו גוף הוא אינו מוסיף חומש o dilma keivan
de'be'oto guf hu eino mosif chomesh or do we say since in
the end of the day it's still the same object, the same
body, you don't add a fifth. So what would you say? תיקו
teiku we don't know. So anyway there's a very complicated text. I
ran through that pretty quickly but as you can see it's you
know they're constantly editing back and forth but the essence is to
make it like the first like the first version. So the basic
point is that when you redeem something and it's in a second
thing you add the fifth once you don't add a fifth the
second time. But also then so that means if it's the old
one that's already had a fifth added you don't add the second
time. How do you define old and new? And the question is
what if it was in a second animal but it also transferred
from an אשם asham to an עולה. olah. Okay now the גמרא
Gemara now the גמרא Gemara goes on. All right. בעי רמי בר
חמא. ba'ei Rami bar Chama. Now we can put all of those
complex cases of אשם asham aside, we're done with them. Back to
תמורה tmura but we're also going to discuss חומש chomesh as well
because both in תמורה tmura and in חומש chomesh there's a question
about who the special thing that happens about the adding of the
fifth or the ability to do תמורה. tmura. So let's take a
look. בעי רמי בר חמא. ba'ei Rami bar Chama. מקדיש מוסיף חומש
או מתכפר מוסיף חומש. makdish mosif chomesh o mitchaper mosif chomesh. And
now we get to the question that really has been at the
heart of the משנה mishna that we were looking at you know
the before the few like two משניות mishnayot back. Who is considered
the owner of the קרבן? korban? So the before this we had
the question about if a כהן kohen is the owner of the
of the בכור bechor or it's like he's bringing the בכור bechor
but he's not the owner. But now we get even to a
more at the heart of it. Let's say one person sanctifies it
but it's being used for another person. Who is considered the owner?
So when it's בדק הבית bedek habayit you don't have that scenario.
Sanctifying it means just writing a check over to the temple. But
by a קרבן korban you do, right? A קרבן korban always is
in that funny middle state that it's holy and it's sanctified but
it still relates to me. I'm bringing it as a קרבן. korban.
Which is why when it's קדשים קלים kodshim kalim you could have
the position of רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili that it's ממון
בעלים, mamon ba'alim, that it's really considered mine. So here nobody's actually
saying it's it's literally yours in the sense of you know whatever
you can sell it to somebody or whatever but who's considered the
owner for the purposes of adding a fifth and the ability to
do תמורה? tmura? Because the Torah says when the owner redeems it
he adds a fifth. The owner does the תמורה. tmura. Who is
the owner? I sanctify this קרבן, korban, this animal, for to be
used for Charlie, that to be Charlie's עולה, olah, Charlie's חטאת. chatas.
Who adds a fifth if it gets a blemish and you have
to redeem it? Who is the has the ability to do תמורה?
tmura? Yes Charlie.
Well there's also many of the קרבנות korbanot fulfill halakhic obligations for
an individual.
Right. But but even if you're obligated in a חטאת, chatas, if
I sanctify my sheep it doesn't become your חטאת. chatas. If I
sanctify it for you then it does become your חטאת, chatas, it
will satisfy your halakhic obligations. Right, but it still was my sheep
and I was the sanctifier. So who is considered to be the
owner of the קרבן? korban? There's no question you're the one that's
going to get credit for it. That's what it means to sanctify
it for you. But who's the one that's the owner for the
purposes of adding a fifth and תמורה? tmura? That's the question.
So like let's say hypothetically you know I'm
I'm sanctifying this as a חטאת chatas for for you and then
whatever it is like you know then I just don't give it
to you. Do you actually bring me to court?
I don't know. That maybe gets more into the question about whether
it's ממון בעלים mamon ba'alim in קדשים קלים kodshim kalim and within
רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili that says קדשים קלים... kodshim kalim...
ממון בעלים *Mamon Ba'alims* presumably he would say that's a good question.
First of all within רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi הגלילי *Rabbi Yosi HaGlili*,
presumably who the ממון בעלים *Mamon Ba'alims* that it is, is the
one who is the מכפר *Mechaper*, not the מקדיש makdish, *Makdish* because
he his whole of that so within רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi, הגלילי
*Rabbi Yosi HaGlili* for קדשי קלים *Kodshei Kalim* I could bring you
to court. Otherwise no, because I don't own it enough דיני ממונות
*Dinei Mamonos* to demand it in court, but there's still a question
of who's designated as the owner for the purposes of adding a
fifth and תמורה temurah *Temurah*.
Meaning no, if you can't bring me to court then you're not
the owner then you've been...
No, no, because the part of the nature of קרבנות Korbanot, *Korbanos*
is, even רבי יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi Yosi HaGlili* only says it by
קדשי קלים *Kodshei Kalim* and people disagree with him, that this is
sanctified. So it's not like your normal sheep. You're not really in
terms of normal civil issues, you don't have the same degree of
control over this and right to use it the way you do
a normal thing, and it's partly owned by הקדש *Hekdesh*, so you're
not considered to be, you know, the official owner as far as
civil issues are concerned. But you're still the בעל הקרבן *Ba'al HaKorban*,
and that means you're the one who the קרבן korban *Korban* works
for, you're the מקדיש makdish הקרבן *Makdish HaKorban*. And the question is
when you get to areas like תמורה temurah *Temurah* and adding a
fifth, meaning within the הלכות halachot *Halachos* of קרבנות korbanot. *Korbanos*, we
recognize a certain person as the owner of the קרבן korban *Korban*.
That doesn't mean with the הלכות halachot *Halachos* of civil court we
recognize the... there has to be real monetary ownership, and that's only
רבי יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi Yosi HaGlili* for קדשי קלים *Kodshei Kalim*.
I mean I would still argue that until you get the כפרה
kapara *Kaparah*, you know, you're like out of the... Okay, that's what
I would...
Okay, but that's not... well first of all for רבי יוסי הגלילי
*Rabbi Yosi HaGlili* certainly not true because of קדשי קלים *Kodshei Kalim*,
and not true here, you have to designate an owner for these
הלכות halachot *Halachos* of the fifth and תמורה temurah *Temurah*. So that's
the גמרא's Gemara *Gemara's* question. So let's take a look. בעי רמי
בר חמא מקדיש מוסיף חומש makdish mosif chomesh, או מכפר מוסיף חומש
*Ba'ei Rami Bar Chama Makdish Mosif Chomesh O Mechaper Mosif Chomesh*. Does
the one who sanctifies it or the one who it is being
atoned for add a fifth? אמר רב אמר קרא *Amar Rav Amar
Kra*, oh, we'll answer with a פסוק pasuk *Pasuk*. ואם המקדיש יגאל
את ביתו *Ve'im HaMakdish Yigal Es Beiso*, if the sanctifier redeems it.
It's right in the תורה Torah *Torah*. מקדיש makdish ולא מכפר *Makdish
Velo Mechaper*, the sanctifier, not the one who it works for. Of
course it makes sense. The תורה Torah *Torah* says it for a
בית *Bayis*. Okay, doesn't matter though. The תורה Torah *Torah*, the תורה
Torah *Torah* when it says who adds the fifth, does not say
אם הבעלים *Im HaBa'alim* that you could have it as a theoretical
question of who's the owner. It designates the person as the מקדיש
makdish *Makdish*. Oh, that's very nice, but that's how he's being described,
so it answers your question. Who adds a fifth? Who does the
תורה Torah *Torah* say add a fifth? The מקדיש makdish *Makdish*. Okay,
so that answers that question. בעי רמי בר חמא *Ba'ei Rami Bar
Chama*, now we have another question. מקדיש makdish עושה תמורה temurah או
מכפר עושה תמורה temurah. *Makdish Oseh Temurah O Mechaper Oseh Temurah*. How
about making a תמורה temurah *Temurah*? Is it the one who sanctified
or the one who's being atoned for? Now that's actually a fascinating
question, right? Because, because you could say, well who has the ability
to transfer the קדושה kedusha. *Kedusha*? Well the answer is nobody, right?
Since you're not able to transfer the קדושה kedusha *Kedusha*, you're just
trying to, right? That's what's so funny about תמורה tmura *Temurah*. You're
trying to, but you don't have the ability. So it's only a
relevant act for somebody who has the ability or who thinks they
have the ability, but nobody really has the ability. So does it
apply to the מקדיש makdish *Makdish* or the מכפר *Mechaper*? So let's
take a look.
או מכפר עושה תמורה tmura. *O Mechaper Oseh Temurah*. אמר רבא Rava
אם תאמר *Amar Rava Im Tomar*, if you were to think that
it goes by the מקדיש makdish *Makdish*, you'll have a problem. Why?
מצינו ציבור tzibur ושותפין עושין תמורה tmura. *Matzinu Tzibur VeShutfin Osin Temurah*
that you could have a case where תמורה tmura, *Temurah* could be
done by a קרבן korban ציבור *Korban Tzibur* or קרבן korban שותפין
*Korban Shutfin*. What would be the case? כגון דשוו שליח לאקדושי *Kegon
Deshavu Shliach Le'akdoshei* that one person sanctified it for the ציבור *Tzibur*
or for the שותפין *Shutfin*. Now why is that a problem? We're
going to learn later on that a קרבן korban. ציבור *Korban Tzibur*,
you can't do a תמורה tmura *Temurah*. Let's say the תמיד *Tamid*,
right? You don't bring a קרבן korban. *Korban* of the ציבור *Tzibur*,
you can't make a תמורה tmura? *Temurah* for it. Now that means
how do you define a קרבן korban ציבור *Korban Tzibur*? קרבן korban
ציבור *Korban Tzibur* is defined by that the ציבור *Tzibur* is the
מכפר *Mechaper*, it works for the ציבור *Tzibur*. So he says if
we say a קרבן korban, ציבור *Korban Tzibur* doesn't, then that means
we're defining the identity as who it works for. Because you could
have a קרבן korban ציבור *Korban Tzibur* that was sanctified by an
individual, right? Yeah, I am taking my perfect עולה olah, *Olah* and
I'm מקדיש makdish *Makdish* it to be used as the תמיד *Tamid*
tomorrow for, for the ציבור *Tzibur*. How does that happen? Well no,
what they really actually do is that they collect the funds and
they whatever. So, you know, so okay, so fine, you could even
have a case, let's say the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, you know,
but you're right actually in that way, it's a question because there
actually has to be an act of
הקדשה *Hakdashah* and a transfer of
funds of everyone.
All right, no, but you can be מוסר *Moser* it to the
ציבור *Tzibur*. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* understands without getting into the
details at least as possible שותפין *Shutfin* is an easier example. I
can be מקדיש makdish *Makdish* my קרבן korban. *Korban* to work for
everybody here in the דף שיעור *Daf Shiur*. Okay, so that's a
קרבן korban? שותפין *Korban Shutfin*, but it's still the definition of קרבן
korban? שותפין *Korban Shutfin* and קרבן korban ציבור *Korban Tzibur* is defined
by who it works for, not who did the sanctification. Even if
an individual did the sanctification. And since we exclude that, you see
we define ownership not by who did the הקדשה *Hakdashah*. If we
defined that then it would be considered a קרבן korban, יחיד *Korban
Yachid* and it would be allowed to do תמורה tmura. *Temurah*, able
to do תמורה tmura *Temurah*. So we're defining it by who is
it working for. Okay, so that's one proof that we define it
by who it's working for. ועוד *Ve'od*, in addition, דאמר רב נחמן
אמר רב הונא תנא *De'amar Rav Nachman Amar Rav Huna Tana*, we
taught in the ברייתא *Braisa*. קרבנו אשם על נזיר Nazir. *Korbanu Ashem
Al Nazir*. This is a פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* by the נזיר Nazir
*Nazir* that he brings... brings the קרבן korban to G-d for his
נזירות, Neziros, when he ends his נזירות, Neziros, מלבד אשר תשיג ידו,
milvad asher tasig yado, beyond what he can afford, in addition to
that which he can afford. And normally when the תורה Torah uses
the word אשר תשיג ידו, asher tasig yado, as you might remember
by ערכין, Erchin, it means that if the person can't afford it,
we can have a sliding scale in terms of how much he
has to pay. Now that's by ערכין Erchin where it's just money
you're handing over. Sometimes we have things like a קרבן עולה ויורד
Korban Oleh V'Yored where also special types of קרבנות, it's not the
norm, but special circumstances where if you can't afford it you can
bring animals of lesser value. So it uses the phrase of what
he can afford by a נזיר. Nazir? But the problem is the
תורה Torah has never said by a נזיר Nazir that you can
change the value of your קרבן korban. and bring a different type
of an animal.
Meaning is there one for if you're a poor נזיר?
Nazir No, that is correct. So the גמרא Gemara says what do
we do with this phrase what you can afford? So there's nowhere
we see that the קרבן korban is on a sliding scale. So
הכי נזיר נידון בהשגת יד? Ha'chi Nazir nidon b'hasagat yad? Is do
we judge the נזיר Nazir. by his ability to afford it? We
don't find that anywhere. הא כיצד? Ha keitzad? So what is the
תורה Torah referring to? Or it means like this. קרבנו להשם על
נזרו, Korvano l'Hashem al Nizro, שהפריש משלו. she'hifrish mishelo. This is the
קרבן korban, he gives to G-d assuming he paid for it himself.
מלבד אשר תשיג ידו, Milvad asher tasig yado, or if he didn't
pay for it himself, then what if he could afford it, then
somebody else paid for him, שהפרישו לו אחרים. she'hifrishu lo acherim. So
basically what it's saying מלבד אשר תשיג ידו milvad asher tasig yado
means that you know that whether he could or couldn't afford it,
what do you mean if he could or couldn't afford it? It
means whether he bought it for whether he paid for himself or
whether somebody else gave it to him as a gift. Okay, so
that's what we're reading into this פסוק pasuk by a נזיר Nazir.
because if you take a step back and realize the whole idea
that I can sanctify an animal to work for you is strange,
right? You wouldn't have thought it was true. I would have thought
if James here needs to bring a קרבן korban and he doesn't
have the money and I want to be a nice guy, I'd
give him my sheep for him to sanctify. But we would normally
assume that you have to sanctify your own קרבן. korban Where do
we get the phenomenon, where do we know such an animal exists,
such a thing exists that you can sanctify your animal for somebody
else? And we're learning it out from this case by נזיר. nazir
It says מלבד אשר תשיג ידו milvad asher tasig yado which we
mean to we read to mean even if you can't afford it,
don't worry somebody else can sanctify it for you. And from there
we learn the idea that somebody can sanctify their animal to work
for someone else.
Unless someone sells you or gives you a קרבן.
korban All right, because that we wouldn't need a פסוק pasuk to
tell me. And now we're going to learn from that certain הלכות
about this. So the גמרא Gemara says למה הלכתא? l'mai hilchata? Why
would the תורה spell out that somebody can sanctify an animal for
me? אילימא לעניין כפרה, i'leima l'inyan kapara, if it's to tell me
that he can sanctify an animal and it can atone for me,
פשיטא דמכפר ליה. pshita d'mechaper lei. Of course it works. Now as
I just said it's not so of course, maybe you have to
sanctify your own animal. So the גמרא Gemara is going to say
that at the end. But now it assumes oh that's taken for
granted somebody can sanctify an animal to be to work for me.
אלא לעניין תמורה, Ella l'inyan temurah,
it must be telling me that for תמורה tmura הלכות it has
the it's the same whether I sanctify it or whether somebody else
sanctifies it. והכי קאמר, V'hachi ka'amar,
here's what the פסוק pasuk says. אף כפי ש af k'fi she
or if you look at the side it's a little bit better
right to the far right. מה כשהוא הפריש משלו עושה תמורה, Ma
k'shehu hifrish mishelo oseh temurah, the same way if you do your
own you can you sanctify your own you have the ability to
do תמורה tmura again not a good thing, אף כשהפרישו לו אחרים
עושה תמורה. af k'shehifrishu lo acherim oseh temurah. So even if somebody
else sanctifies it. So the reason the תורה here is saying that
by the way it could be your קרבן korban, or some or
somebody else could have sanctified it for you, it's coming to tell
you when somebody sanctifies a קרבן korban for you it works just
the same as your קרבן, korban which means what? To כפרה we're
taking for granted, so it's just the same as my קרבן korban.
means that I have the ability to do תמורה tmura by this
the same way I do by my own
קרבן. korban. שמע מינה, Shma mina, בתר מתכפר אזלינן. batar mitchaper azlinan.
So
you see you go by the one it's atoning for.
So the גמרא Gemara says לא, Lo, that's not a good proof.
לעולם לעניין כפרה, L'olam l'inyan kapara, I should say, excuse me, right,
תמורה tmura. is completely the wrong point. Anyway, really we could say
that the תורה is just telling me it works for me. We're
not talking about about תמורה. tmura ודקשיא לך, V'dikashya lach, מתנה דקא
יהבינן ליה, matana d'ka yahavinan lei, you were bothered why do I
need a פסוק pasuk to say it works for me? It's just
a gift. Why can't somebody sanctify an animal to work for me?
That should be obvious. No. אי לאו דרבי רחמנא, I lav d'rabi
Rachmana, מלבד אשר תשיג ידו, milvad asher tasig yado, if the תורה
had not explicitly addressed this case that I can't afford it and
somebody sanctifies it for me, הוה אמינא, hava amina, I would have
said גזירת הכתוב היא. gzeirat hakatuv hi. It's that's the way the
תורה describes קרבנות. קרבנו מדידיה הוא דמכפר מדאחרינא לא, Korvano mididei hu
d'mechaper mid'achrina lo, which is exactly what I would have said, right?
I would have said you what does it mean to have a
קרבן? korban, It means you sanctify your animal, not somebody else sanctify
their animal for you. I wouldn't have known that such a thing
was even possible. קא משמע לן. Ka mashma lan. So this teaches
me that such a thing is possible. This actually is quite nice
because we always deal with תמורה tmura, a lot, we're dealing with
this case of somebody sanctified an animal for me and because how
did חז"ל Chazal even know that such a thing could work as
a קרבן? korban, So we get it from this פסוק pasuk by
נזיר. But now we don't actually have the same strength of this
answer that by תמורה tmura you go by the one working for
the מתכפר, mitkapeir, maybe this is going by the מקדיש, although רבא
seems to have a good proof from the case of שותפות shutphus
and ציבור that the definition of ownership was the one it's working
for, and that's how we're going to conclude.
We learn from נזיר to everything else?
That this, that this phenomenon exists, yes. That such a קרבן korban
can, can exist. מאי הוי עלה? Mai havei alah? So what was
the פשט pshat of this? What was the conclusion? תא שמע, Ta
shema, come and hear, דאמר רבי אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, d'amar Rabbi
Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, מקדיש מוסיף חומש, makdish mosif chomesh, the one
who sanctifies adds a fifth, like we said before, if you might
remember we quoted this at the very beginning of the מסכת, masechet,
ומתכפר עושה תמורה, umitkapeir oseh tmura, the one who it is working
for, the one who it is atoning for, is the one who
can do a תמורה. tmura, Now I must say again that that
is pretty strange because
there is one case where, and I actually didn't get a chance
to check the הלכה. halacha. So I said on the one hand
you can understand why the גמרא Gemara doesn't know the obvious answer
to this because if you just ask, well, who has the ability
to redeem it, the answer is nobody has the ability to redeem
it. So who, who thinks they have the ability, who would have
the assumption they would? So we're saying fine, the מתכפר mitkapeir is
considered the owner to do the תמורה. tmura. But there actually is
a case where somebody does redeem a קרבן, korban which is when?
When it has a blemish, right? So let's ask that question. I
sanctify my, my sheep to work for James here and it gets
a blemish. Who can redeem it? Can I redeem it? Can James
redeem it? Can either of us redeem it? Well, you can't redeem
it. You have nothing, you can redeem something with בדק הבית bedek
habayis because בדק הבית bedek habayis definitely is the owner then they're
interested in selling it and getting the proceeds. Right here you have
to have a relationship to it.
I mean I,
I would think either can do it. Right. So maybe it's either.
I don't, I actually don't know the answer to that, okay? I
have to check that up. But you would think that the same
answer to that is the answer of who can do a תמורה,
tmura because that's the person who under other circumstances is in the
position to actually transfer and effect the קדושה. kedusha, Now there is
a difference and we've pointed this out before and it's worth mentioning
this another time, that there is an irony here that if the
animal has a blemish, I'm, I'm allowed to redeem it and redeem
it directly on, I have to redeem it on another animal, but
I can't do a תמורה tmura, on another animal even when the
first one has a blemish. What's the difference? What's redeeming, what's a
תמורה? tmura, And to some degree the answer is just the words
I use. Do I say this is an exchange or this is
being redeemed? Conceptually a little bit sharper the way it's explained is
that if I'm redeeming it's saying I'm removing the קדושה kedushah from
this and placing it on the other. An exchange is I'm saying
I start with the other and say let this one take the
place of that one. But it's funny, such a subtle difference and
one thing is what I have to do when it has a
blemish and the other thing is, is a לאו. lav. But anyway
the reason I just point this out is because there is a
subtle difference between redeeming and exchanging conceptually, one could argue that when
it has a blemish who can redeem it is not necessarily the
same person who does the תמורה. tmura. But it is strange. The
גמרא Gemara raises the question of who does the תמורה tmura. and
I would have thought that it's the same answer as who can
redeem the animal. Because that's the person, I don't know who it
is, but you would have thought that we might have had some
discussion of who it is. Okay? So I would, maybe the answer
is that it is the same. But that's just interesting that we're
discussing who can do the תמורה tmura, without addressing the question of
when it has a blemish who can redeem it. Yes.
Does the ownership extend to both the original owner and the person
who it's being brought for or is it transferred?
Well, that's exactly the question. So for the purposes of תמורה tmura.
we know it's being transferred. But for the purposes of, you know,
of redeeming, maybe since I originally instilled the קדושה, kedushah maybe I
can redeem it if it gets a blemish. Now again intuitively I
would say that no, that once I've sanctified it for James and
it's his, the, and it's now, you know, his interest in bringing
that קרבן korban and he is, so he is the one also
that if it gets a blemish, what's the problem it gets a
blemish? Now he can't bring his קרבן. korban But I sanctified it,
I walked away, I gave him this gift, I walked away, I
sanctified it. Now it's got a blemish, it's his problem, so presumably
it's also true that the מתכפר mitkapeir is the one who does
the redeeming. I would imagine it's the same point. But it is
interesting that the גמרא gemara is not addressing it.
So, so the original owner could no longer do תמורה temurah then,
that's why they say, that's the
point here, that the original owner could not do תמורה. temurah That's
the conclusion. Okay? And my question is, is that what about the
question of who can do redeeming when it gets a blemish, shouldn't
that be the same question or at least a related question? And
I'll try to find the answer to that, but it's again, it's
interesting the גמרא gemara asks the תמורה temurah question without addressing the
redeeming question.
Yes. Concerning redeeming and adding a fifth, there's,
well you always add a fifth when you redeem.
But didn't we just say that when you add the fifth that's
the,
yes, but we were talking about בדק הבית bedek habayis where anybody
can redeem. I sanctify my car to the temple treasury. Now they're
having an auction, they're selling the car, they're trying to get proceeds
from it. So there everybody has a right to redeem. If I
happen to be the owner or the מקדיש I should say, I
add a fifth. But when it talks about an animal that gets
a blemish, if my קרבן korban, has a blemish, you can't, somebody
can't come off the street and redeem it on another animal, right?
Right, but it says that
the מקדיש adds a
fifth. The מקדיש adds a
fifth. Oh, one minute. I see, you make a good point. Hold
on.
Okay, so you actually make an excellent point. You're right, you're right,
I wasn't thinking. When I was talking about מקדיש מוסיף חומש, makdish
mosif chomesh I was thinking about בדק הבית. bedek habayis. But you're
right, the גמרא gemara, says is that the מקדיש or the מתכפר.
miskaper. So the גמרא gemara when it talks about the מקדיש מוסיף
חומש makdish mosif chomesh, is asking the question, is assuming that, that's
a very good point, is assuming that when I sanctify even an
animal because it's talking about מתכפר, miskaper, even a קרבן, korban that
the original owner can do the redeeming.
That's who it would even be a question.
So, so then it is, so that's a very good point, you're
right, I wasn't even thinking about that, I mean that the מקדיש
is the exact same case of a קרבן korban for somebody else.
So yeah, I stand corrected, James makes an excellent point. So now
you actually have a particular irony. I sanctify this קרבן korban. for
James. It gets a blemish. I am in a position to redeem
it. And when I do redeem it, I add a fifth. So
even though I'm the one who can redeem it, when I try
to do a תמורה, temurah. it's a meaningless act, and the act
of תמורה temurah. is only meaningful when he does it. So the
only remaining question I have is, are you in a position, I
guess you have to be in a position to do the, to
do the תמורה, temurah or else it wouldn't have asked the question
who has the fifth, because I'm the only one who can do
it anyway. So okay, James is actually quite correct. So what we
actually implicit,
I could show you if you want the way,
implicit from the earlier גמרא, gemara thank you very much, implicit from
the earlier גמרא gemara is, I sanctify this animal to work for
James, it gets a blemish, either of us can redeem it, because
the גמרא gemara asks the question which one of us adds a
fifth. You're right, I wasn't thinking, connecting those two, but you're right,
absolutely right. Since the גמרא gemara, asks which one of us adds
a fifth, the גמרא gemara assumes that either of us are in
a position to redeem it. Okay, so thank you, that's a very
good point.
Not asking just who can redeem it at all.
No, then it wouldn't have said who adds a fifth. Presumably the
question is both can redeem it, which one of you adds a
fifth. So now, thank you, so okay, now actually you're right, what
is implicit from this גמרא, gemara or pretty much explicit, I just
wasn't thinking, from this גמרא gemara is, is that I sanctify an
animal to work for James, both of us are in a position
to redeem it. If I redeem it, I add a fifth, if
he redeems it, he doesn't. And now that both of us are
in a position to redeem it, so we could have imagined that
both of us could do a תמורה. temurah It would have been
meaningful to do a תמורה temurah. for either of us to have
done a תמורה, temurah and nevertheless the answer is no. When it
comes to the act of תמורה, temurah. James is the one that
is considered to have the power. When it comes to the adding
of a fifth, I'm the one that's considered to be the one
who adds the, I'm the מקדיש or more of the owner to
add a fifth. When it comes to who can actually redeem it,
the answer is both of us. So thank you very much, you're
right, that is definitely the פשט pshat of what's implicit in the
previous statement. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara says מאי הוי עלה,
mai hava ala, so what was the upshot? תא שמע, ta shema,
come and hear, דאמר רב אבין אמר רבי יוחנן, d'amar Rav Avin
amar Rabbi Yochanan, מקדיש מוסיף חומש, the one who sanctifies adds a
fifth, ומתכפר עושה תמורה, umiskaper oseh tmura, the one who it's working
for is the one who does the תמורה. temurah And תורם
משלו על של חבירו, torem mishelo al shel chaveiro, now why did
they add this? This wasn't even part of the discussion, but very
often the גמרא gemara likes doing things in threes. Okay, so I'm
serious, that's probably why the third point was added. And here's the
third point, תורם משלו על של חבירו, torem mishelo al shel chaveiro,
if you have a similar case where I take my תרומות ומעשרות
trumos u'maasros from my grain to exempt your grain, grain, so therefore
I, so okay, that's very nice of me, טובת הנאה שלו, tovas
hana'ah shelo, I now have the right to decide which כהן kohen
and לוי levi gets the תרומות ומעשרות, trumos u'maasros, because I was
the one that took it, even though it worked for your grain,
it was still my grain that's becoming the תרומות ומעשרות. trumos u'maasros.
מאי טעמא דקרא, mai ta'ama d'kra, את כל מעשר תבואתך ונתתה, es
kol ma'asar tevuascha v'nasata, that when you take the מעשר ma'asar of
your grain, then you shall give. So if the תרומות ומעשרות trumos
u'maasros were actually coming from my grain, although they were exempting yours,
but they were coming from mine, I get to decide who it
goes to. All right, so that was very nice. So what we've
concluded there was fascinating issue exactly about that, that yes, that there
is this phenomenon, you can sanctify an animal to be a קרבן
korban for somebody else, as we've just made clear. Thank you very
much, there was the, the, it seems like, you know, it's pretty
clear that both parties are in a position, the sanctifier and the,
and the one who, and the one who works for it, to
redeem it. So they both have that implicit power. So therefore you
could have imagined that both of them make a תמורה. temurah But
nevertheless the גמרא gemara concludes and the גמרא gemara. seems to assume
that only one of them, and chooses that which one is the
one who it's working for, as opposed to who adds a fifth,
that's the one who sanctified it. Let's take a look now at
the next
משנה. mishna. אין ממירין לא איברים בעוברים, ein memirin lo evarin b'ubarim,
you cannot do תמורה, not limbs with fetuses. Obviously there's a little
play on word here, איברים בעוברים. evarin b'ubarim. ולא עוברים באיברים, v'lo
ubarim b'evarin, or fetuses with limbs. ולא עוברים ואיברים בשלמים, v'lo ubarim
v'evarin b'shleimim, and not fetuses or limbs with whole animals. ולא שלמים
בהן, v'lo shleimim bahen, and not whole animals with them. What does
all of this mean? Let's take the first example of the whole
animals, which is easy. I've got my animal here which is a
קרבן, korban... and I say I am trying to exchange for this
קרבן korban the leg of that sheep. Now, we've already said I
can exchange sheep for goat, I can. It's the act of תמורה.
תמורה when I exchange sheep for goat, cows for sheep, one for
a hundred, a hundred for one. So now we're saying what if
it's a partial thing? This קרבן korban, I am I'm exchanging I'm
exchanging the sheep of this the leg of this sheep for this
קרבן. korban. Does it work? שלמים באיברים. shelemim be'eivarim. What about I'm
exchanging this sheep for the fetus, the calf that's in this mother's
womb right now? Does it work? Now, does that mean I can't
sanctify a leg, I can't sanctify an עובר? ubar? Maybe I can.
Right, right, right, we're going to see. Maybe I can. But I
can't do תמורה because and we'll see later I'm just jumping ahead
a little bit, at least by תמורה the פסוק pasuk says בהמה
בבהמה, behemah be'vehemah, an animal for an animal. So you could understand
that the exclusion is even if you could sanctify a leg and
sanctify a fetus, but it's not בבהמה, be'vehemah, it's not a whole
בהמה. behemah. The פסוק says בהמה בבהמה. behemah be'vehemah. Good. So that's
not שלמים shelemim for them. What's them for שלמים? shelemim? The reverse.
I sanctified I did sanctify a fetus as a קרבן. korban, And
now let's presumably that worked. And now I'm going to say the
קדושה kedushah. of that fetus I'm exchanging now for this nice, you
know, one-year-old sheep. Doesn't work. Why not? Again, בהמה בבהמה. behemah be'vehemah.
I'm not an עובר ubar בבהמה. be'vehemah. Somehow if I sanctified a
leg and now I want to exchange it, that's not תמורה. בהמה
בבהמה behemah be'vehemah and not a leg בבהמה. be'vehemah. So those are
the cases with שלמים. shelemim. And once that's true, how much more
obvious is it that I can't do an אבר eivar for an
אבר eivar or an אבר eivar for an עובר ubar or an
עובר ubar for an אבר, eivar, right, any of those any of
those things because that's even doubly not בהמה בבהמה. behemah be'vehemah. Okay,
so that those things do not work in the act of תמורה.
Yes.
A fetus just born and then is therefore a full animal, then
would the תמורה take effect?
The fetus, yes,
assuming that that is considered to be an animal in its own
right and not ולד קדשים vlad kodashim and we'll talk we'll talk
about that when we get to the משנה. mishnah. So maybe. The
answer is a definite maybe. Yes.
Can we go back to our conversation in the גמרא Gemara before
if you said like דבר שאין הנשמה תלויה בו davar she'ein haneshamah
tluyah bo is it a בהמה? behemah?
So a little bit. But let's take a look at the end.
But again, this is not necessarily a question of does קדושה kedushah.
work. It's what תמורה and based on the פסוק of בהמה בבהמה
behemah be'vehemah which might have a narrower definition. So let's look at
what רבי יוסי responds to this. I'm רבי יוסי, I'm רבי יוסף,
Rabbi Yosef, רבי יוסף, Rabbi Yosef, ולא במוקדשים האומר רגלה של זו
עולה כולה עולה. Velo bemukdashim ha'omer raglah shel zo olah kullah olah.
If you were trying to sanctify an animal and you said the
leg of this is an עולה, olah. you can't limit it to
the leg. Once you designate the leg, the whole animal is defined
as an עולה. olah.
אף כשיאמר רגלה של
זו תחת זו תהא כולה תמורה תחתיה.
Af kesheyomar raglah
shel
zo tachat zo tehei kullah temurah tachteiha. Okay, so let's see what
he argues. So if that's true, אף כשיאמר רגלה של זו תחת
זו תהא כולה תמורה תחתיה. af kesheyomar raglah shel zo tachat zo
tehei kullah temurah tachteiha.
So if you therefore say that this leg will be in exchange
for this קרבן, korban, so fine, it's like I sanctified the leg.
And since if I sanctified the leg I made the whole animal
a קרבן, so trying to exchange the leg and have the leg
take the place of the קרבן is like the whole animal trying
to have the whole animal take the place of the קרבן and
it does become a תמורה. Okay. You could try to understand what
he's saying a little bit more, meaning in terms of not the
לאו lav of the תמורה but the effect of תמורה. If the
effect of תמורה is that we look and an attempt to transfer
from A to B really has the effect of sanctifying B, that's
normally what the effect is. I tried to transfer from A to
B, they're both קודש. kodesh. So it has the effect of sanctifying
B. So if I try to transfer from A to a leg,
it has the effect of sanctifying the leg. What would happen if
I sanctified the leg? The whole animal would become קודש. kodesh. So
therefore here too. But presumably he's not just saying that it's קודש,
kodesh, presumably he's saying also that you transgressed the לאו. lav.
And to answer my question, if you say ראשה, roshah, so it's
ראשה roshah then it means the same thing. Well, קל וחומר, kal
vachomer, he's doing even a leg.
Let's take a look now at the גמרא. Gemara איתמר, Itmar, it
was said. בר
פדא אמר אין קדושה חלה על עוברים. Bar Padda amar ein kedushah
chalah al ubarim.
So let's talk before we get to תמורה whether it works by
קדושה. kedusha Can you directly sanctify a fetus? Okay, very straightforward question.
בר פדא Bar Padda says you cannot. רבי יוחנן אמר קדושה חלה
על עוברים, Rabbi Yochanan amar kedushah chalah al ubarim, you can directly
sanctify a fetus. Okay. ואזדא רבי יוחנן. Ve'azda Rabbi Yochanan. So if
according to בר פדא Bar Padda you sanctified a fetus, it meant
nothing. The animal was born, you would if you tried to bring
it as a קרבן you'd bring חולין לעזרה chullin la'azarah unless you
sanctified it again. Okay, or here's that's one נפקא מינה. nafka mina.
Here's another נפקא מינה. nafka mina. I sanctified the pregnant mother, the
whole mother with its fetus. According to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, it's
like I sanctified the mother separately and the fetus separately. The sanctity
applies directly to the fetus. According to בר פדא, Bar Padda, no,
the sanctity only applied to the mother. When the fetus is born,
it has a status of ולד קדשים, vlad kodashim, a child of
a קרבן but not something that was directly sanctified. And ולד קדשים
vlad kodashim has different הלכות in terms of when it can be
brought and so on than something directly sanctified. Okay. Can you just
do what you want then, right, to בר פדא? Bar Padda? No,
ולד קדשים vlad kodashim has קדושה. kedusha, Okay, but that's when I
sanctified the mother with the fetus. So it's a double debate. When
I sanctify the fetus directly did it do anything? And when I
sanctify the pregnant mother with the fetus, is it fundamentally a sanctity
of the mother or is it a sanctity both separate sanctity. on
the mother and on the fetus. So let's take a look. ואז
רבי יוחנן לטעמיה אמר רבי יוחנן, Va'az Rav Yochanan l'taimei amar Rav
Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan goes to his reasoning, because רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan said הקדיש חטאת מעוברת וילדה, hikdish chatat me'uberet veyalda, you
sanctified a pregnant חטאת chatat and it gave birth. So there you
go. רצה בה מתכפר רצה בולד מתכפר. ratza bah miskaper ratza bevlad
miskaper. You can use either one. Now normally what's the הלכה halacha
of a ולד חטאת, vlad chatat, Michael? מיתה. misa. So one of
the five חטאות chatas that have to be let die is I
sanctify a חטאת, chatat, it's a female and it goes ahead and
it gives birth, so this thing which is a derivative קדושה kedusha.
of the חטאת chatat can't be used for any other קרבן, can't
be brought as a חטאת, chatat, it's only the derivative קדושה, kedusha
I have to let it die. That's what בר פדא Bar Pada
would say. You sanctified this pregnant animal, the mother was the חטאת,
chatat, the child was not sanctified on its own terms, it was
a ולד חטאת vlad chatat מיתה. misa. But רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says no, it's like I sanctified two animals. What would happen if
I took two sheep in front of me and I said both
of these are for my חטאת? chatat? I only have one חטאת
chatat that I'm obligated. Both of these are for my חטאת. chatat.
What's the הלכה? halacha? The הלכה halacha is is that I can
choose which one to bring as a קרבן and we're not dealing
with derivative קדושה. kedusha. Not right, what happens exactly to the other
one we won't talk about right now, but the point the first
point is I can choose I can choose which one to bring.
מתכפר בה ובולד? miskaper bah u'bevlad?
Well no, because this is actually a case where I designate one
to be באחריות.
b'achrayus. So actually what I do is I let that is a
case where I can allow one to graze, get a blemish and
redeem it. That's when from the very beginning it was designated to
be a backup, a backup for the other. So that's what רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says that if you
sanctified the mother with the fetus, they both have direct קדושה kedusha.
and I'm allowed it's not a ולד חטאת, vlad chatat, it's a
direct חטאת, chatat, I'm allowed to choose which one to use, the
other one I wait to get a blemish. ולד חטאת vlad chatat
would occur even if the mother wasn't pregnant at the time you?
Yes, yes. And for and for בר פדא Bar Pada it makes
no difference. But for רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan if it was pregnant,
it's like I sanctified it directly. So the גמרא Gemara says וצריכא,
u'tzricha, you have to tell me both cases. The case of a
of where it's a pregnant mother and the case of direct meaning
and you sanctified the mother or the whole package as that was
the second case, and the first case was you tried to only
sanctify the fetus. And you have to tell me they argue on
both cases. דאי אשמעינן בהך קמייתא, de'ee ashmeinan behach kamaisa, if you
had just told me their debate in the case of just sanctifying
the fetus, התם הוא דאקדשיה לעובר גופיה, hasam hu de'akdishei l'ubar gufei,
that's where you are sanctifying the fetus itself. אבל הכא דאקדשה לאימיה,
aval hacha de'akdishah l'imei, but when you are sanctifying the whole package
with the mother, הא ככולה אימיה וקדש, ha k'chulah imei v'kadosh, maybe
I would say that even בר פדא Bar Pada would agree, excuse
me, even רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would agree that when it's the
whole package we fundamentally look at it as a part of the
mother. If I focus on it alone, I can give it its
own identity. But if I focus on the entire package, then I
look at it as just part of the mother and it doesn't
have its own קדושה. kedusha, So maybe רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would
have agreed to that case. So we say no, even in that
case he says it has its own קדושה. kedusha. ואי אשמעינן בבתרייתא,
v'ee ashmeinan b'basraisa, if you just told me the case of the
mother and the fetus at the same time, the whole package, I
would have said התם הוא דאקדשה לכולה דאית בה, hasam hu de'akdishah
l'chulah d'is bah, I'll go maybe that's only the case רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan says. Why? Because maybe there, since you're able to be
מקדיש the mother, so you can also have the power to be
מקדיש the fetus even on its own terms. But you start from
a fundamental ability to be מקדיש something because you're relating directly to
the mother. אבל הכא דאקדשיה ליה, aval hacha de'akdishei lei, but if
I only trying to sanctify just the fetus, כיון דליתא אבראי לא
קדיש, keivan d'leisa abra'i lo kadosh, since it's not on the outside,
it's only on the inside, it's not visible, maybe I can't relate
to it at all, maybe I can't sanctify it, צריכא, tzricha, you
need to tell me both cases. What? No, no, both of these
are within רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. It's a there's an element of
חידוש chiddush in each case of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. In the
case of the of the fetus, I would have said of the
of the one minute, in the case of the pregnant mother, I
might have said yes, the whole thing is קדוש, kadosh, but since
the emphasis is on the mother, maybe the fetus doesn't have its
own inherent קדושה, kedusha. maybe it's only coming derivative from the mother,
in that case it's only looked as part of the mother. So
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying no, even in that case you
sanctify the fetus alone. On the other hand, if you had just
told me in that case I sanctify the fetus, I would have
said I'm able to sanctify the fetus because I'm getting a piggyback
on sanctifying the mother. But if I try to directly sanctify the
fetus, I can't relate to it and therefore it doesn't. So it's
not both sides, it's just saying with רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, there's
a חידוש chiddush either way to say I'm able to sanctify the
fetus alone. One that I'm able to relate to the fetus alone
when I'm not relating to the mother, and the other that when
I'm relating to the mother, it's not seen as part of the
mother. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this, לישנא אחריא, lishna
achraya, here's another version, אם שיירו משוייר ועובר ירך אמו הוא. im
shiyaro meshuyar v'ubar yerech imo hu. So here we first conceptualize what
רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan point is. Number one is you can separate
off the fetus from the mother. So for example, and this is
an interesting question, can I do the reverse? Can I say if
I can sanctify the fetus separately, if when I sanctify the mother
and the fetus each one is considered to have their own independent
sanctity, can I sanctify the mother without sanctifying the fetus? Okay, and
the answer is yes. So conceptually what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is
telling you is you can leave it over. It's not part of
the mother, which then means עובר לאו ירך אמו. ubar lav yerech
imo. It's really not two things, רש"י Rashi essentially it's one, רש"י
Rashi really combines the two. We see it as fully independent. And
that's the fundamental חידוש chiddush of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Therefore, I
can sanctify the fetus separately, the mother separately, and when I do
them as a package, each one has its independent קדושה. kedusha Okay,
so that's a nice conceptual explanation of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. And
now we're going to say why I need both cases. לתרתי למה
לי, letarki lama li, why do I need both cases? צריכא, tsricha,
you need it. דאיתמר בהא משום דאמי חזיא לגופיה. de'itmar beha mishum
de'imei chazya legufei. So if it said only the case where the
mother, pregnant mother, and I did the whole package, since the mother
is fit for itself, the sanctity works on the mother, מיגו דנחתא
קדושה עלה, migu denachas kedusha alah, since anyway I can sanctify the
mother, נחתא נמי לולד, nachas nami levlad, it empowers me to sanctify
the fetus. So but maybe only because I start by sanctifying the
mother, which is something I can obviously do. Then I'm able to
also sanctify the fetus independently, but only through my power to sanctify
the mother. But if it were אבל אידך לא, aval idach lo,
if I was only trying to sanctify the fetus directly, maybe I
can't relate to it right now. It doesn't, you know, it's not
exposed, I can't relate to it. קמשמע לן kamashma lan that I
can sanctify the fetus directly. הדר, hada, so it tells me that.
דאיתמר בהא, de'itmar beha, if it just said the case of sanctifying
the fetus directly, I would say משום דקמפיש קדושה על הולד, mishum
dekamafish kedusha al havlad, that's because you're explicitly designating out the fetus
for separate קדושה. kedusha אבל ההיא לא, aval hahi lo, but if
you sanctified the whole package, I would say then in that case
we'll interpret it as a קדושה kedusha, on the mother and not
as a separate קדושה kedusha. on the ולד. vlad. צריכא, tsricha, so
you need both cases. Okay, so that's again basically the exact same
thing with maybe a little bit clearer or a little differently phrased,
but basically according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan they're always seen as
independent entities and even if I sanctify them both with one קדושה,
kedusha. they have their independent קדושה. kedusha, Okay, now let's take a
look about trying to prove one way or the other within this
debate of whether the ולד vlad has separate קדושה. kedusha, Okay, איתיביה
רבי ירמיה לרבי זירא. eitvei Rabbi Yirmiya le-Rabbi Zera. So רבי ירמיה
Rabbi Yirmiya asked רבי זירא. Rabbi Zera. כיצד מערימין על הבכור? keitzad
maarimin al habechor? How can you sort of, sort of do a
scheme on the בכור? bechor? Okay, meaning how can you... That's exactly
what I wanted to ask and then I looked two lines ahead.
Okay, what, what were you going to ask? I was going to
ask what, how can you sanctify something that's going to automatically become
a בכור? bechor? Oh, that's not the question. I mean, well, the
question, the way that's going to be the, the case, yes. But
the question here is because then you could have just said it
wasn't a בכור bechor case. The question here is what are ways
you can get out of בכור? bechor? Right. It's a funny way,
funny way for the משנה Mishnah to be out there. Anyway, what
are ways you can get out of בכור? bechor? So one way,
one way, one way you can get out of בכור bechor is
by sanctifying the fetus before it's born. Okay, and therefore בכור bechor
only applies if the, both the mother and the fetus are non-קדשים.
kodshim. But if one of them is קדש, kodesh, the בכור bechor
doesn't apply. So if you want to get out of בכור, bechor,
you're still going to have to... You're still going to have to
give up the animal, but you won't have to give it to
the כהן. Kohen. So you sanctify, so you sanctify it before it's
born. That's what the משנה Mishnah says. So let's take a look.
כיצד מערימין על הבכור? keitzad maarimin al habechor? How do you scheme
around בכור? bechor? המבכרת שהיתה מעוברת, hamavakera she'hayeta me'uberet, you have an
animal which is מבכרת mavakera meaning it's the first time it's going
to give birth and now it's pregnant. אומר, omer, so you say
the following: מה שבמעיה של זו עולה. mah shebe'me'eha shel zo olah.
So I'm sanctifying what's in its, you know, the child's an עולה.
olah. That's only if it's a male though. Right, I understand. But
it's only going to be a בכור bechor if it's a male.
Right. Okay, so if it's a female, if it's a female, right,
then you have to sell it and use the money for an
עולה. olah Right. Okay, if it's a female then you, then you're
פודה podeh it and use the money. So you don't totally get
out because if it's 50-50 and if it's a female you're going
to have to bring a קרבן you might not have wanted to
bring. Okay, yes. I would have tried to sanctify it as שלמים
shelamim because then I can get more benefit from it. Yeah, that's
an interesting question. That's an interesting question. Okay, I don't know why
it
gives that as an example.
Okay,
so, anyway, ילדו זכר הרי זה עולה, yaldu zachar haveizeh olah, and
then you get out of בכור. bechor. אלמא קדוש עובר. alma kadosh
ubar. So you see that the fetus has its intrinsic sanctity. This
is a proof for רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. You're directly talking about
the fetus and you're sanctifying it. According to בר פדא Bar Padda
that was a meaningless act. So right, you can't sanctify the fetus.
You can sanctify the mother and the fetus can have derivative קדושה,
kedusha but you can't sanctify the fetus. So how do you deal
with that? So אמר ליה, amar lei, כי מתניתא היא בקדושת דמים.
ki matnita hi bikdushat damim. No, no, no. That's not talking about
sanctifying it to be brought as an עולה olah. itself. That's talking
about that you're
sanctifying it to sell it and to use the money for an
עולה. olah. Now that's a little bit funny why that makes a
difference. At the end of the day, that would work. At the
end of the day, you're still sanctifying the fetus. בר פדא Bar
Padda says you can't sanctify the fetus. But it seems like here's
the difference. Why can't you sanctify the fetus? I mean, is it
because it doesn't exist? It does exist. You can't sanctify it because
you can't give the identity to a fetus as a קרבן. The
identity of a קרבן is something that a... applies to a live
animal. Okay, this is not yet a live animal, it can't have
that identity. But as when I sanctify something for its value, I
don't care what it is, I just care that it has value,
right? So I can sanctify my car for the proceeds should go
for an עולה. olah, So I can sanctify my car that the
proceeds should go for an... I can sanctify the fetus. It doesn't
have to be an animal. I'm not trying to bring the thing
itself, I'm just trying to sell it and use the proceeds. So
therefore, yes, you can relate to the fetus as long as you're
not trying to treat it as an animal. So if you're only
going to sanctify for the money to be used as an עולה,
olah, that you can. Can you sanctify the leg of an animal?
For its proceeds, for the דמים damim to go for an עולה,
olah, presumably yes. Yes, because then you're not again, you're not trying
to give it its... it's not an identity sanctity as it were,
it's just an ownership issue essentially, you know, so... so when you
fundamentally talk about the value, then you can do these types of
divisions. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: Ah, so the גמרא
says one minute, if that's all you're doing, מי אלים קדושת דמים
דמפקע ליה מבכורה? mi alim kedushat damim demapka lei mibechora? Is that
really true? That if it's not a fundamentally קרבן... I understand that
a קרבן can't be a בכור bechor because the animal is fundamentally
something else. But if it only is a question about selling it
and using the proceeds and it's not an identity change, right? You
understand, if I sanctify this thing, you're just going to remove the
קדושה, kedusha, sell it, take the proceeds, etc., etc., בכור, bechor, you
haven't changed the identity of this object. If it's not an identity
change, he says, does it really get out of being a בכור?
bechor? Is that really true? אמר ליה, amar lei, אין, in, yes.
והתנן, vehatnan, and here's a משנה: Mishnah: כל הקדשים שקדם מום קבוע
להקדשן ונפדו, kol hakodashim shekadam mum kavua lehekdeshan venifdu, all... all sacrifices
that you had a blemish before they were sanctified and then they
were redeemed. So remember, when it has a blemish before it's sanctified,
the sanctity was never קדושת קרבן. kedushat korban. The sanctity was only
קדושת דמים, kedushat damim, money to, you know, sell the proceeds and
to use it for a קרבן, but it never has that sense
of קדושת קרבן kedushat korban itself, that... that identity type of a
sanctity because it started with a מום. mum. Okay, so it's like
sanctifying my car for a קרבן. I sell it and I use
the proceeds. So what do I do after I redeem it? חייבים
בבכורה ובמתנות. chayavim bebechora uvamatnot. Then after it's redeemed and it gives
birth, then I would, you know, I'm obligated in בכורה, bechora, if...
if I שחט shacht it, I have to give זרוע לחיים וקיבה.
zroa lechayayim vekeiva. It's like complete חולין chullin because the קדושה kedusha
has been completely removed because it was only קדושת דמים. kedushat damim.
If you remember, that was a big משנה, Mishnah, that was a
big difference. If I sanctified it and it got a blemish, since
it started with קדושת הגוף, kedushat haguf, even after I remove the
קדושה, kedusha there's some remnant of that קדושה kedusha. left. But if
it started with a מום mum and then I redeemed it, after
I've redeemed it, the קדושה kedusha is completely removed because it was
not about an identity, it was only about value and that's completely
been transferred away. Okay, so very nice. So how is that relevant?
So he says, read this closely. He says, after it's redeemed, it's
exempt from a בכור. bechor. Okay, טעמא דלאחר שנפדו, taama delachar shenifdu,
I mean it's obligated in בכור. bechor. After it's redeemed, it's חייבים.
chayavim. That's when it becomes obligated in a בכור bechor because you've
completely removed the קדושה. kedusha. אבל קודם שנפדו פטורים. aval kodem shenifdu
peturim. Before it's redeemed, it's exempt from a בכור, bechor, although its
קדושה kedusha, is only קדושת דמים, kedushat damim, only value קדושה. kedusha.
אלמא, alma, you see, דאלים קדושת דמים דמפקע ליה מבכורה, dealim kedushat
damim demapka lei mibechora, that קדושת דמים kedushat damim is strong enough
to exempt you from בכור. bechor. Very, very nice proof, right? Okay,
so how do you deal with the problem that the עובר ubar
can be קדוש? kadosh? Ah, קדושת דמים. kedushat damim. When you're not
relating to it as an animal, just as a thing that has
value, and it's so therefore, because it's not about making it a
קרבן, just about the value being... going towards a קרבן, that you
can do even by פשט דמצוה pshat demitzvah and therefore, and that
is enough to exempt it from a בכור. bechor. And you're obligated
to eventually redeem it? Yes. And then you have to bring it
as a... and then you have to bring it as a בכור.
bechor. Oh, so then the question would... no, because again, remember, it's
only חייב בכורה chayav bechora if that happened after it was redeemed.
If when it was born... if when it was born... the moment
of בכור bechor is when it's born. If when it's born it
has the קדושה, the קדושת בכור kedushat bechor doesn't take effect on
it because at that moment it has קדושה. If you redeemed it
when it was still in utero and then it was born, then
it would be like we said, after it's redeemed, now it can
be חייב. chayav. But no, but it doesn't mean that the חיוב
בכורה chiyuv bechora is hovering and waiting to take effect. The key
moment is when the animal is born. Okay, and that moment you
say, is it still sanctified or has it already been redeemed at
this moment? Whether you're talking about the fetus or whether you're talking
about the mother. Is that based on that משנה? Mishnah? No, well
that's based on other assumptions, that בכור bechor is based on the
moment the animal is born, whether it's the status of the mother
or the status of the fetus. Okay. So as long as you
redeemed it after it was born, it's never בכור. bechor. Exactly. Okay,
same if you redeem the mother after the mother gave birth, it
will never change the status of the child. Okay. Now the גמרא
says like this: איתיבי, eitivei, let's try to get in one more
case. האומר מה שבמעיה של זו עולה, haomer ma shebimeia shel zu
olah,
you say what's the...
the fetus that's in this animal's... you know, this fetus is an
עולה, מותרת בגיזה ואסורה בעבודה. muteret begiza vaasura baavoda.
Now not the fetus, you're not going to do גיזה giza on
the fetus. You can shear the mother, but you can't work the
mother. Okay, if you sanctified the animal inside, why? Because shearing the
mother has no impact on the fetus. Working the mother actually can,
you know, make the... affect the health of the fetus and therefore...
Okay, so so why so. Okay, משום כחוש עובר *mishum kichush ubar*
because שבא *sheba* because by working the mother, the mother's in קדש
*kodesh* just the animal, you are weakening the fetus. Okay, so then
it seems like a perfect case that you're directly relating to the
fetus and you're making the fetus an עולה *olah* and it works
and you have to therefore be concerned about its status. אמר ליה
*amar leh*, הני מילי קדושת דמים *hani mili kedushas damim*. Oh, we're
not talking that you're making the fetus an עולה *olah*, we're meaning
that you're sanctifying it for the proceeds to be used for an
עולה *olah*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, ומי אלימא קדושת דמים דאסירא
ליה בעבודה *umi alima kedushas damim de'asira leh ba'avodah*? So who cares
about it? It's קדושת דמים *kedushas damim*, why would it make it
forbidden to work the mother? It's not an intrinsic קדושה *kedushah*, it's
only for its value. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, אמר ליה אין
*amar leh in*, yes, דתנן *detnan* we taught in the משנה *Mishnah*,
יוצאין לחולין לגוזז ולעבוד *yotzin lechulin legozez vela'avod* that if you actually
redeemed, if you sanctified this animal with a blemish, right, if you
take another case, an animal with a blemish you sanctified it, so
if it started with a blemish, its whole קדושה *kedushah* is only
קדושת דמים *kedushas damim* and so now when you remove the קדושה
*kedushah*, you've completely removed it like we said before. What's one implication
of completely removing it? You can shear it and work it. When
I remove the קדושה *kedushah* from an animal that first was sanctified
and then had a blemish, the remnant of קדושה *kedushah* that remains
is that I can't shear it and I can't work it. But
if it only started with קדושת דמים *kedushas damim* and I remove
it, now I can shear it and work it. But what's the
implication? Before I remove the קדושה *kedushah*, I can't shear it and
work it. Okay, so it says it
again, like if you redeem it, I sanctify an animal without a
blemish, gets a blemish and I redeem it. Because it started with
קדושת הגוף *kedushas haguf*, even now that I've redeemed it, some of
the remnant of קדושה *kedushah* says I can't shear it and I
can't work it.
I can still eat it just normally, שחט *shecht* it and eat
it, but I can't shear it, I can't work it. Right. If
it started with a blemish and I sanctified it, it was only
קדושת דמים *kedushas damim*, when I remove the קדושה *kedushah* I remove
it completely and now, now I'm allowed to shear it and work
it. But before, implied, before I couldn't shear it and work it.
Okay, so it says, הקודם שנפדו *hakodem shenifdu*, טעמא משום דנפדו *ta'ama
mishum denifdu*, it's because they've been redeemed. הקודם שנפדו *hakodem shenifdu*, before
they've been redeemed, אסורין בעבודה *asurin ba'avodah*, you can't work them. אלמא
קדושת דמים אסורין בעבודה *alma kedushas damim asurin ba'avodah*, so you see
that קדושת דמים *kedushas damim* is prohibited with עבודה *avodah*. So once
again, we have answered it by saying although it sounds like you're
sanctifying the fetus as a קרבן *korban*, it's really just for the
value to be used towards that end and the same type of
effect, at least in these two cases about exempting from בכור *bechor*
and preventing גיזה *gizah* and עבודה *avodah* would be true even if
it's just קדושת דמים *kedushas damim*, even if it's not קדושת הגוף
*kedushas haguf*. We will continue with this tomorrow.